Guide to the Edward Parmelee Smith Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward Parmelee Smith papers
1849-1947
MS 1136
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
The papers consist of miscellaneous personal papers of Edward Parmelee Smith including letters to his future wife (1851-1854) and letters to his daughter (1872-1873) with an account of a sea voyage to California and his impressions once there. His years at Yale College are documented by an autograph album with messages from his teachers and classmates (1849-1855). Among the four photographs in the papers is one showing Smith with six students when he was president of Howard University, Washington, D.C. (1875). Clippings and correspondence describe his work as Commissioner of Indian Affairs (1873) and his death in Africa in 1876 while an envoy of the American Missionary Association.
Smith, Edward Parmelee, 1827-1876
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection also available on microfilm (314 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM109.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 109 instead of the originals.
Biographical / Historical
Edward Parmelee Smith, son of the Rev. Noah Smith (Dartmouth Coll. 1818) and Laura (Parmelee) Smith, was born in South Britain, a parish of Southbury, Conn., where his father was pastor, June 3, 1827. On the death of his father, in Oct., 1830, he was taken to the home of an uncle, Col. Ashbel Smith, of Hanover, N. H. He entered Dartmouth College in 1845, and this College two years later.
After graduation, he taught school for three years in Mobile, Ala., and then began the study of theology in the Yale Seminary. In March, 1853, he removed to N. Y. City, and studied in the Union Theol. Seminary, laboring also in connection with the Children's Aid Society, until the fall of 1854, when he went to Andover Seminary for the closing year of theological study. After another year spent in preaching in Rockville, Conn., and Pompey, N. Y., he was ordained pastor of the Congregational Church in Pepperell, Mass., June 11, 1856. In Jan., 1863, he offered his services to the U. S. Christian Commission, and was employed, at first as one of the General Field Agents and later as Field Secretary, until the closing of the work of the Commission, in January, 1866. He had, meantime, resigned his pastorate in 1864, and now entered the service of the American Missionary Association (devoted especially to educational work among the Freedmen) as District Secretary at Cincinnati. In 1867 he was called to N. Y. City as General Field Agent of the Association, and in that capacity performed a large share of the work of planting schools for freedmen in the South. When President Grant in 1871 invited cooperation in the work of Indian civilization, Mr. Smith resigned his position in New York, and offered his services as Indian Agent. He was appointed to the Chippewa Agency in Minnesota, and remained there until unexpectedly offered the position of Commissioner of Indian Affairs of the U. S. Government in April, 1873.
This position he resigned in 1875, and was immediately elected President of Howard University, in Washington. He accepted the Presidency, and in the spring of 1876 sailed for Africa, on invitation of the American Missionary Association, to survey and report on the work of their missions in that country. He left Sierra Leone in May in good health, but while on board the steamship Ambric on his way from Monrovia (in Liberia) was taken with the African fever, and was too ill to land at Accra, as he had intended. He died on shipboard, in the Gulf of Guinea, near the island of Fernando Po, on the night of June 15, and was buried on the 16th at the Presbyterian Mission Station, Old Calabar.
He was married, June 3, 1856, to Hannah C., daughter of Levi Bush, of Westfield, Mass., who survives him with one of their two children.
(Taken from Yale Obituaries, 1871-1880\).
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of miscellaneous personal papers of Edward Parmelee Smith including letters to his future wife (1851-1854) and letters to his daughter (1872-1873) with an account of a sea voyage to California and his impressions once there. His years at Yale College are documented by an autograph album with messages from his teachers and classmates (1849-1855). Among the four photographs in the papers is one showing Smith with six students when he was president of Howard University, Washington, D.C. (1875). Clippings and correspondence describe his work as Commissioner of Indian Affairs (1873) and his death in Africa in 1876 while an envoy of the American Missionary Association.
African Americans; Indians of North America; Missionaries -- United States; California -- History -- 1850-1950; Clergy; Missionaries; Smith, Edward Parmelee, 1827-1876; Smith, Hannah Cleveland Bush; United States. Bureau of Indian Affairs; Howard University; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1849
- Inventory
  - Autograph album, Yale College, 1849 (Box 1, Reel 1U)
  - Three ALS to Hannah Cleveland Bush, [1851-1852?], 1854 (Box 2, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Andover Association: license to preach, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Three ALS to Hannah Cleveland (Bush) Smith, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
  - Eight ALS to Gertrude Smith, 1872-1873 (Box 2, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - ALS to Henry M. Tenney, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - ALS to Hannah Cleveland (Bush) Smith, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Dictated letter to G. H. White, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Passport, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Letter of credit, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Lock of hair, undated (Box 2, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Printed obituaries and illustrated description of grave, 1876, undated (Box 2, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
  - Harry A. Stimson: ALS and clipping of speech, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - C. Crosby: ALS to Gertrude Smith, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - First Parish in Pepperrell, Massachusetts: booklet and leaflet relating to the 200th anniversary, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Photographs
    - Edward P. Smith in Winona, Minnesota, [1872?] (Box 2, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
    - Edward P. Smith with six black students at Howard University, undated (Box 2, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
    - Memorial plaque, [1949?] (Box 2, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Clipping relating to appointment to the presidency of Howard University, [1875] (Box 2, Folder 11, Reel 1U)